[music]
>> Well, this is Samuel Colvin, creator of
Pydantic,
uh creator of Monty as well most
recently, um also CEO of Pydantic the
company,
um creator of LockFire, Pydantic AI
gateway, Pydantic AI, and my boss.
So, please everyone, a warm welcome to
Samuel Colvin.
>> [applause]
>> Thank you so much. Being Lisa's boss is
definitely the scariest of those of
those things. Um
Yeah, I'm going to talk about Monty, uh
a project I started uh just at the very
end of last year. I had a bunch of
conversations with people, particularly
Anthropic, and got me thinking uh about
what was going to happen
uh
I thought soon, indeed I was right, and
so soon after I'd had those
conversations,
um a bunch of articles came out, and and
code mode became a thing, or what what
is kind of now often referred to as code
mode.
So, the the principle here is that code
execution, giving your agent the
capacity to write code,
is an excellent idea until you actually
have to go and do it.
Um
Why is it a great idea? Well, there are
there's a whole bunch of uh articles on
it, but in particular um
Cloudflare call it uh code mode, um the
idea that instead of exposing all of the
tools that you want your agent to be
able to call to the agent, you expose
one tool, which is run code, and that
code can effectively call those tools as
functions.
Um Anthropic call it uh programmatic
tool calling, and also talk about using
code execution in front of MCP, so
instead of exposing all of the tools
available
uh directly into the context, you allow
some code execution in between.
There's even a coding agent called small
agents from Hugging Face that's been
around for some time that does a similar
thing.
The problem is how do you go about
running that code?
Um
you have a bunch of different choices
for how you how you execute code. And so
uh I call this continuum from uh
impotence to chaos, but but the idea
here is that like actually despite that
like slightly aggressive and
controversial name, everywhere on this
continuum there are useful things to be
done. My point is not that there's no
economic value at one particular point,
but just that the only things need to
happen. But basically fundamentally we
we um
when we give more capabilities, when we
give more power to what the coding agent
can do, we basically forfeit uh control
and we increase the amount of context
that we need to that we need to have.
And lots of in particular lots of the
uh tasks where using code is valuable
are not
uh full computer use. We do not need to
be able to go and run bash and use
pandas or polar or uh curl. We actually
just need to be able to go and write a
little bit of code. Whether that be
Python or TypeScript doesn't really
matter. I think there are some
compelling reasons why Python is
slightly better, but it doesn't really
matter, right? The point is that we give
the the agent the capacity to go and run
code, um
they can perform very well even if you
don't have like all of the libraries
they might ever want to install.
Um
uh
and so
um
uh but but in particular if you want to
go and do that, there is no trivial way
to add um
to to allow an agent to go and run run
Python code. We have
uh the option of just running the Python
code on the host where where your agent
is running. Well, that's kind of
dangerous because now that code can
ultimately access everything that your
agent can access. Um we can go and use
the sandboxing services which are kind
of great and that's what lots of people
are using right now and they're growing
crazy. The reason they're growing is so
fast is because it's actually quite
expensive at scale. But it's a it's a
really big problem for enterprise. If
you are
a bank or a large hedge fund, you can't
just go and like put your credit card
into Daytona or Model and suddenly have
as many containers as you want. And so
it's one of those bus tub situations
where sandboxes are great for your like
well-funded startup, but they're bad for
someone who doesn't have have the
resources and they're also really bad
for enterprise. Um and so the the idea
behind Monty was to find a kind of
middle way, a way where we could run
Python code without all of the overhead
of creating an entire uh VM, basically
inventing a whole Linux machine just so
that you can run some Python code. So
Monty is a minimal secure Python
interpreter written from scratch in Rust
specific to specifically to let AIs
write code.
Um so very simple hello world example
here. Um here we are calling Monty from
inside Python. So we can install it with
Pynatic Monty.
Uh and here we have a very simple
example where we're just doing hello
world with an F string. And if I go and
run this,
it will run and you that is that is it
actually running. The point is that the
the latency in particular of doing this
because Monty is running in the same
process
on the same machine as the as the agent
or as the the code that's calling it is
in the order of 1 microsecond.
Whereas when you're using sandboxing
services, that's often 1 second. So
we're getting kind of six orders of
magnitude improvement in latency to
start running code.
Um
So what exactly uh can and can't Monty
do?
Um it completely blocks access to all of
the all of the machine. The idea here is
we have not taken CPython and basically
chopped bits off it until we think it is
safe. Instead, we've started from
scratch and built an entirely new
interpreter. So it it lacks lots of
features bluntly, but it does mean there
is no access to
uh to the file system, no access to
environment variables, no access to
third-party packages, no access to
networking unless you explicitly go and
add those functionalities.
Um and then we allow calling uh the rest
of the environment via this uh uh
callback system. But those callbacks are
not the the typical system where you
would take a function pointer, pass that
into Monty, and it would it be able to
go and access it. Instead, we do
something actually quite like um
how coding agents uh call tools. We
return from execution and say, "Please
call this tool with these arguments."
And that means that the host gets
complete control over what it does at
that point. Um and one of the one of the
other neat things, because we built
Monty from scratch, is you can go and
snapshot it. You can basically call
dump, and you get back the binary
representation of the interpreter, which
you can go and put into a database. And
again, that is orders of magnitude
smaller than taking an entire VM and
trying to like compress it and put it
into object storage.
Um so that gives us this kind of durable
execution. I've talked about latency.
Because it's just written from scratch
in Rust, we can run it anywhere where we
can run Rust code. We don't need Python.
There's already a JavaScript library.
There's a Dart um implementer a Dart
SDK. Someone's implemented a Go SDK and
a Kotlin SDK already. So anywhere where
you can run Rust code, you can call
Monty.
Um and the the most important bit here
is we don't need another sandbox. Or
once Monty is mature, there is no need
for an extra sandbox. You can go and run
that code directly where your agent is
running.
Um but there is a trade-off. This is not
designed to be an alternative to
CPython. This is not I am not suggesting
you can take your Python code and port
it to Monty and it's going to work. That
is not our goal. There is a graveyard
full of people who have tried to build
alternative interpreters for Python, and
they have all, for the most part,
failed. Because to be a genuine you can
um
take your existing code that runs with
CPython and map it into whatever other
runtime, you need 99. a lot of nines of
uh compatibility before that's really a
credible thing to do. Monty is like not
even one nine, I would say, of
compatibility. There's a lot of things
you can't do, but if you tell the agent
exactly what it can and can't do, um it
it's amazing how far it can get.
Um and so uh the one other thing I
didn't mention was it also comes with
TY, the type checker from Astral, I
suppose now from Open AI, but hopefully
it stays good. Um,
uh, built in as well. So, it can run
type checking on your code before it
runs it. In particular, it has its own
version of type shed, so it can
specifically say to the runtime, "You
can't use X." So, if you try to import a
module that's not implemented, it will
give you, uh,
an error at typing time saying you can't
go run that code.
Um, and so, yeah, I think it's important
to say that like the golden rule is
Python is the truth,
uh, and we speak nothing but the truth,
but we are not trying to speak the whole
truth. In other words, we're definitely
not going to do anything that you can't
that is invalid Python, but there will
be lots of things that are valid Python,
but don't work in in Monty.
So, I don't know how I'm doing, uh,
on time, but I'm going to
Oh, cool. I've got some time. Um, uh, so
I think the other kind of fundamental
differentiator from this, and it's fair
to say that there are some other
projects in the same vein. There's a
thing called Just Bash from Vercel,
which is a terrible misnomer. It is not
Just Bash. It is Bash and
all of the as much as possible of the
Linux, uh,
ecosystem of tools, because that's what
what you need to run kind of bash-esque
tasks. Um, there's another one called
BashKit, but I think, uh, Monty is the
only of the like,
And then there's also QuickJS, which is
a similar kind of concept in in
JavaScript, but, um,
the idea with all of these projects is
instead of taking something that exists
and chopping bits off it until we hope
it is secure, you start with something
that can do nothing, and then you add
functionality on to to allow it to do
things. That means it it will be more
limited, but it means it should
conceptually be safer long term. It's
like having a white list rather than a
black list.
Um, so quick demo here. Let me Let me
give some quick context for this demo.
We had, uh, this happened to Pyodide
AI's downloads. We suddenly had this
like
weird jump in the number of downloads
uh, in February. Like this is already
doesn't look like it, but this is
already quite a lot of downloads where
like roughly a million downloads a day.
And then
And suddenly there's into a big query my
often spend hours figuring out the
sequel to work out what exactly went
wrong. Or I could just go and give
access to the sequel to a to a coding
agent and go and ask it basically figure
out what happened.
And that works pretty well. And in my
particular case I actually did this with
code code and it worked out.
But if you were doing something
equivalent in a application context, you
don't need an entire VM to go and solve
this problem. Monty allows you to
basically run the sequel you need,
process the data, investigate what's
going on, loop over the output, and find
out the problem without the need for a
VM.
So that's what we have here. I won't go
through all of the code, but like
uh one interesting thing we do here is
we generate the stubs for the the the
external functions that that that are
available and we add those stubs both to
the the context of the the system prompt
for the model, but also we use those
stubs
in the in the when we call the model as
as the
stubs that are available when we do type
checking. So that we can have full type
checking, prompt about what what the
model um can and can't do.
Um
we have a Palantir AI agent that's
ultimately going to go and run this
code. But the interesting bit comes down
here where we basically set up these
four functions, which are what are
registered, and these are the functions
we say you can go and call them. So if
you look at what they look like,
I hope we have the we have the SQL query
um function here. Now this is where it
gets interesting because I said that
there's a very minimal amount of stuff
you can do inside Monty, but that allows
us but that doesn't mean we can't use
for example DuckDB because we just
register external functions that can do
whatever you like within Monty and now
it can have it can have
gated white-listed access to whatever
you want it to have access to. So here
we're going to use
DuckDB to run some sequels against the
parquet files.
Plotting again. Obviously, there's no
map plot lib support within Monty, but
we can have a function called plot,
which allows it to go and generate a
plot and and output the the image and
even render it on screen
um from within Monty.
Couple of others for showing plots and
displaying a table, but you get the
idea.
Um and so ultimately, our agent would
just iterating iterating over
until we get to the agent thinks it has
finished and then it will output and and
tell us what it thinks has happened.
The actual running Monty comes here.
We're going to run it like this. One of
the things we discovered when building
Monty was that coding agents are very
very sorry, LLMs are very very strongly
trained to expect a REPL. EG when they
are asked to run Python code, they
assume that functions they've defined or
variables they have defined in previous
steps will still be available. And so we
had to go and just implement the REPL
inside Monty because fighting the the
training of the models that they wanted
a REPL didn't work. So that's why we're
using REPL mode here. Um at the moment,
I have to run type checking as a
separate step, but that that won't be
around for long.
And then obviously, if we get an error,
whether that be a runtime error or a
typing error, we just like serialize
that error, give it back to the model
and tell it go figure it out.
So so if I go and run this example now
and the gods of demos are with me and I
have internet connection,
uh
we will hopefully see see what's going
on.
Uh and so it will think for a bit
working out what sequel it what Python
it needs to run.
And
I'm going to be confident say it's going
to work at some point.
Maybe Anthropic is down.
Uh
internet connection is there.
It's thinking real long and hard.
Um I can look at actually inside log
file what's going on.
And you see that it is indeed Opus that
has been thinking for 28 seconds.
Uh definitely didn't do this just
before. I can actually do a um Blue
Peter style here's one I made earlier if
this decides it doesn't want to work. I
can look at the previous run here
where you see that Opus thought for
3.8 you can see here 3.3 seconds
and you can actually go and see the code
that it ran.
And so if you it's kind of quite
interesting to watch the the journey of
the code that it that it went through.
So you see here we have excuse me
the the main prompt here where we told
it what it can run and we gave it the
the type hints to the external functions
it could call
and then it output you see the very
simple sequel it ran at the beginning
got back some some schema some data
about the schema of the the sequel table
and it used that to go and go and run
the queries.
And
I don't know what it's done. It's gone
Oh, it's now running. And it it's
I'm going to start it again and hope for
the best. I don't know what happened
there.
Uh
because what it should be able to do is
well as the printing out the sequel it's
running it should be able to Now it's
running.
Um
it should also be able to generate the
charts to to show you what it's looking
at as it's going along. And you can kind
of see the sequel it's generating and
you can see this is relatively
sophisticated. This is not just and it's
printed out a chart of of downloads over
time as it starts to investigate.
Um
it can do relatively sophisticated
things just with the with the amount of
Python we have now and we're adding more
as we go along. This is already powerful
enough to do a whole range of tasks with
external functions. It's already found
that the there was a spike in downloads
of the metadata file which is kind of
the
uh the telltale sign that this was some
weird weird usage not not real
downloads.
Um so it will carry on and at some point
finish and tell me that there was some
weird spike in metadata downloads but
uh that's what I've got. Thank you very
much. Any questions? I'm around at the
end.
>> Wonderful. Thank you. Are you sure you
you you have
time for one question? Oh my goodness,
that's good timing.
>> [laughter]
>> If you want, you see I see a few people
trying to get in. Come on, give them
>> Done. One question here.
>> Yes.
Thank you. How far and where do you want
to bring Monty to? What is the vision
behind it in 5 years' time? Maybe like
>> Oh goodness me. Goodness, that is where
we're going to be in 5 years' time. One
year. I mean, one thing I should have
said that I didn't mention in this is
this is a This is This is not a slot
fork of Python
because it's not a fork. It is slot,
right? As in this is mostly AI
generated, right? Um and this this
project would not be possible if it
wasn't for the like leading models which
can go and like implement large chunks
of it.
I am not trying to go and build a
CPython alternative. I am not going to
go and add ABI compatibility so you can
load third-party modules. I think there
are definitely some obvious things we
want to go and add some other third some
other standard library um packages um
libraries um
We At the moment, there's no classes.
It's amazing how far it gets without
being able to implement classes because
they're actually for
much more like code design than actually
this kind of uh execution still going. I
I um the the number one thing we want to
do is get it to the point of confidence
where we can say it's no longer
experimental and you can go and use it
and run unsafe code, which at the moment
we we probably wouldn't give that
guarantee. That's the That's the number
one goal. After that, good question. How
about external services? So, external
things working with Monty together. Like
what? Uh I don't know. Any integrations?
Any I don't think we need them because
the point is you can do external
function calls for virtually anything.
There were There are a few places where
it would be nice to be able to wrap any
arbitrary Python object and pass it in.
That's exactly what That has some limits
in terms of the um durable execution
context, but I think that would be a a
non non non crazy thing to do. Although,
definitely it with like security
concerns.
Thank you.
Should I stop there?
Wonderful. Thank you. Yeah, I think I
think so. So,
thank you, Samuel.
>> [applause]